[Music]
w
good evening good day everybody I hope
you're all doing very well and welcome
back to the ask abijit show it's episode
170 that we are on um first of all I
would like to thank you all for for
helping the channel reach 800,000 8 lakh
subscribers it's all thanks to you so
thank you so much I really appreciate it
I really value your viewership so thank
you so much and uh yeah I hope you're
all doing very well it's been a it's
been a while a couple of weeks two three
weeks since I did this so it's great to
be back on the live stream and to
restart the show it's not really ended
but yeah there we are so let me see who
all is there on on the live chat I can
see Tes hi uh Echo rishab rajput Kushi
in blood mahit gai sidhart Shri sham
Shri Ram upadhi Dean shal midnight
stalker Nirvana Green Day fan suut takur
Pavan Kumar Singh Bas dunger Singh Johan
Welcome Back
Sir Atara AI abinav SG Arjun
nandakishore
tiari that One MA praa paramita harid
borya Alpha metas Shashank gorav Nik
onuka
AI Yash J VI Kumar milin dandar sidhar
rites Omar aaat Singh abishek
shav Dutch vanderlind God of Thunder vs
Big Tree Mazer chacher hello V Jer
prush who Al who who else is there g g g
guep Ani
anud best thing rajash sharan
influencing World Shri Tang Shashank
smash Priyanka jwar jitu Shad sir white
meat SG Kel Aman wakil P Raju Sager B
dri Mato Perez and and so many other
people so I will not be able to greet
you all individually by name but thank
you so much for being on the live stream
and with that let us get into the
questions so let's go ask me your
questions I'm going to take questions
from the live stream from the live chat
only uh so that there is more
interactivity and you can get I mean
lots of you often say that when I select
questions from the comments many of your
questions haven't taken so maybe this
will give you the opportunity to ask
questions and maybe I can pick up some
of some more of those so there we are
and with that let's take some questions
so let's go fire questions and I'll take
as many as possible okay let's begin
with something that
is about physics we haven't done that
for in a while so sidar Singh rajur says
tell us something about the Andromeda
and Milky Way Collision Theory well it's
not a theory it's a fact it's
observational evidence you know uh the
Andromeda galaxy is the closest galaxy
to the Milky Way and to us right we can
see it with the naked with with the
naked eye it's kind of faint and blurry
but it's visible to the naked eye if you
if the Galaxy was a little bit brighter
it would be larger than the moon when
the moon shines in the sky the Andromeda
galaxy would be larger but it's it's far
it's faint and that's why it's not that
visible people may not really pay
attention to it but it's there it's
there in the night sky it's visible and
we know from measurements of blue shift
red shift all that you know that the
Galaxy is coming closer and closer it's
moving towards us and based on the
distance that it's moving towards us
which we can calculate by the blue shift
which see what's blue shift what's red
shift it's the Doppler effect applied to
light applied to photons so when
something you know the doter effect
right when a train is coming towards you
the Whistle the the the siren it sounds
higher pitched and it's when it's moving
away from you it sounds lower pitched
and similarly the same thing can happen
to light the same thing applies to light
wavelength frequencies all that so we
can tell that the Andromeda Galaxy from
the blue shift uh that we see when we
you know take like measurements we can
see that it's coming towards us and we
can measure how fast it's coming so it
is coming towards us the the two
galaxies the Milky Way and the Andromeda
and Andromeda is slightly larger the two
galaxies are coming towards each other
they're moving towards each other
because of the force of gravity and
because they are they are so close close
together the uh expansion of the
universe is not able to counteract the
two galaxies coming together okay So
eventually I don't know how how long it
will take but in a billion two billion
years or so whatever it is I don't
remember the exact number right now but
the two galaxies will eventually not
Collide but they will merge there'll be
no Collision there'll be no hard
smashing Collision galaxies are mostly
empty space you know so the galaxies
will will come together they'll they'll
merge there'll be this dance this Cosmic
gravitational Galactic dance some Stars
will be flung around and all that but
eventually after another billion years
or so there'll be a settled the things
will settle down so somewhat and you
will have a much larger merged Galaxy
that will emerge out of this and the
name that's been been given to it is
milk coma or something like that yeah so
yeah that's what's going to happen it's
not a theory we know it's happening the
two galaxies are moving closer together
as we speak right now as we speak it's
happening it's not a theory it's going
to happen so that's in brief about the
eventual not Collision but merger of
these two galaxies which is like way in
the future we don't have to worry about
it not going to happen in our lifetime
so hopefully if humans are around
there'll be if humans are still around
in a billion years or whatever time it
takes we're going to be very different
from what we are today and our
descendants with will think of us as the
way we think about Homo erectus or
whatever right like almost monkey like
primitive creatures yeah so that's uh
that's about that now let's see other
questions
um was cousin marriage prevalent in bhat
during the time of the epics you mean
the ramay and the Mahabharat well um
that's something I'm not really sure
about I'm not sure cousin marriage is
something that was very prevalent in
India at any given point in time in
certain sections of society in the
subcontinent cousin marriage is kind of
prevalent today I think it is not
something that's advisable from a
medical genetic perspective a cousin is
rather close genetically right I mean
it's a cousin so yeah I'm about the Vic
period about the ramayan mahab period
I'm not really sure if there was any
such
thing uh I think think cousin marriage
this this custom which is a fringe
custom in the subcontinent not in all
areas in some areas of the
subcontinent Pakistan let's say it's
kind of quite prevalent so clearly it it
came into India from outside from a
different culture right so I don't think
it's it's ever been part of our
culture so I'm not sure if it was ever
prevalent in India before the uh tur
invasions
um so yeah that's what I can say I'm I'm
not it's not a question that I've ever
pondered on or thought about so yeah
that's what I can say I'm assuming it
wasn't there I'm assuming it wasn't
prevalent it's quite sure that it's
quite clear that it this this custom
entered into India VI the turkic
invasions you know that was the medium
there was a vector by which this thing
entered India and I don't think it's
really prevalent in India it's
definitely prevalent in Pakistan and you
see that the Pakistani population has
all these birth defects and all which
come comes from in breeding I mean you
marry your own cousin and you have kids
with him or her you're going to have
defective you're going to have defects
in your Offspring and I mean that's
that's just genetics you know it's just
standard medicine that's what you what
you taught in your mbbs or whatever so
yeah you see that in Pakistan I mean the
quality of the
genetic of the genes is isn't isn't
great because of this so yeah all right
let's take another
question um
um Back To
Nature uh put some light on Quantum
healing techniques becoming prevalent in
the scientific world now there is no
such thing I'm sorry to burst this
bubble there is no such thing as Quantum
healing or Quantum Consciousness or
Quantum
whatever uh typically when you hear this
sort of terminology it's it's the sign
of somebody trying to pull the wool over
your eyes you know this new age all this
stuff they going to heal you through
Quantum methods and all no that's not
how it works see the world we live in is
a macroscopic world it's not a all of
the properties of the universe that we
inhabit they seem apart from the
gravitational thing okay all of the
other properties of the world arise from
the laws of quantum mechanics for
example if you hold a crystal in your
hand it's a purely macroscopic Quantum
object but well our skin our clothing
the world around us it's macroscopic it
obeys the laws of Newtonian mechanics
but there is a Quantum element to it as
well because everything emerges from
that but Quantum healing Quantum
Consciousness all of that that is voodoo
hand waving nonsense I'm sorry if if it
upsets some people but that's simply a
fact okay I mean I do know about what
quantum physics is what quantum
mechanics is and what it is not there is
no such thing as Quantum healing so this
is not prevalent in the scientific world
it's prevalent in the pseudo scientific
World okay uh that's the long and the
short of it so yeah if it upsets some
people I do not mean to upset you but
facts simply are facts
unfortunately uh all right
uh
okay okay suraka L please say something
about mizoram international border with
Myanmar what's happening it's a mess
yeah good
question uh good question and it I'm not
sure if I should talk about this but
yeah let me give you a brief overview of
what's happening this is a sensitive
matter this is a sensitive geopolitical
matter it's not a local thing that's
happening it's a geopolitical thing okay
so to understand what's happening we
have to look at the map here we are the
map is back so uh let's let me put the
map on the screen and then we will
talk here's the map so in case some of
you are not aware where mizoram is where
where Myanmar is well you have to look
at India's Far East which everyone calls
the Northeast because of colonial
reasons and then you have the state of
mizoram and Manipur these two states
this is where all the well that's where
the mess is and it's not mizoram that's
messed up it's Manipur that's messed up
Manipur I mean half of Manipur at least
is under foreign occupation essentially
okay
and understand why this is happening
this is not something the current
government has this mess has not been
created by the current government this
mess has been created by the
incredibly
policies that the Indian former Indian
governments previous Indian governments
have implemented since
1947 okay so the mess is because of that
and of course it it all started in the
1850s or thereabouts with the British
occupiers of India they messed this
place up so what's happening right now
there is a government in Myanmar okay it
is a military government it's you could
say the military H they call it people
think of it as the janta it's not the
janta it's the Hun that's the term J N
ta it's an Spanish term so you have a
military dictatorship in Myanmar okay
and you have various forms of res
resistance to this military
dictatorship so we have and then you
have the chin State the chin state is
something that borders
muram and that's where you have the
Chinese origin people who live there
okay these people are the
Chino ethnic group also known as the
cookies also know known as the zi and
the misos all right this is a Chinese
origin ethnic group they originated
somewhere in the Yan region or Beyond in
present day China and they somehow in
the past in the recent few centuries
they moved into this region and these
kin zo cookie Zoo zoi People whatever
they are this entire grouping of
individuals this people they are not
Burmese okay they are mainly located in
Burma but they are not burmes they do
not practice Burmese culture they don't
speak the Burmese language and they are
fighting the Burmese government okay and
they want to create a nation of Their
Own and these are the people who have
during colonization British occupation
of the region because the British also
occupied Burma so during the British
occupation of this region they converted
these people to Christianity so they're
all Christians and they want to create a
nation in Christ and they fighting the
government of Burma but they're also
fighting the government of Bangladesh
and the government of India okay this is
a separatist movement and it has funding
from somewhere okay let's let's call it
somewhere funding is coming in they're
getting arms ammunition social media
support they're getting leadership
support I mean coordination all that
from
somewhere and not from this
region okay that's what's happening now
the burmes government the military
government is obviously fighting against
these people because they want to carve
out a separate country from this region
and the fighting is happening close in
the chin State chin State uh let's see
if we can chin state
Myanmar let's see if we can get a yeah
it's okay you can see it now it's
highlighted over here so this is the
region where much of the fighting is
happening and there's other fighting
happening near the Chinese border as
well the unan border and all it's a big
mess okay the government of Myanmar is
not in total control of the country chin
State apparently it looks like they have
mostly evicted the government of Myanmar
so there is fighting happening there the
myanmar's government is Sometimes using
the Air Force to bomb these separatists
and all that and when this happens there
is this influx of people they call them
refugees apparently who move into the
Indian border who Mo move across the
border into India much of it is
happening in mizoram and then what the
government of mizoram does is that it
doesn't uh take the Biometrics of the
people even though the central
government has told them they have
refused to do it so the mizoram
government is not taking Biometrics and
what they are doing is that they are
simply pushing these people North into
Manipur and then these so-called
refugees they set up villages in man and
they say that we are
cookies and then they they are given
scheduled tribe or whatever status and
then they take over the land so over
half of Manipur is occupied by these
people and we know that they are
fighting a terrorist Insurgency against
the native people of Manipur over half
of Manipur is under foreign terrorist
occupation all right so that's what's
happening right now that's as much I was
as I will say and yeah so it's it's
there is no short-term solution to this
when you have 8 to 10 lakh foreign
squatters on your territory it's not
going to be easy to evict them it's
going to take at least a decade or two
this problem was created over a century
maybe more than a century it started in
the 1850s or so okay after the British
started occupying these territories uh
when the kingdom of Manipur lost its
sovereignty when they had to accommodate
British political agents on their soil
that's when this influx started okay so
the king of Manipur the kings of Manipur
in those days were forced to start
giving land to these foreign
settlers and the government of India
after 1947 after 1949 when Manipur
became uh part of India the government
of India was completely clueless about
the far East of India which which we
call the Northeast so they simply
continued the British policies of
punishing the indigenous people of
Manipur by settling foreigners
okay and that's how and in the last
decade it looks like almost half a
million more terrorists have come and
settle down so that's an ongoing problem
this is going to take time to solve and
these individuals let's whatever they
are the zomi people or whatever they
want a separate nation and they have
tremendous International funding and
backing I mean they are a rag tag bunch
of illiterates okay who have no
allegiance to Any
Nation but they are very well
coordinated they are very well funded
they have inexhaustible apparently
inexhaustible supplies of ammunition and
arms and they have a lot of support if
you see from certain quarters which is
visible on social media in certain
reports put out by think tanks and all
that so this is a geopolitical
issue okay this is designed to
destabilize India to set the Far East of
India on fire and also to destabilize
China that's the weird part of it in the
past the Chinese have funded and
fermented separatist insurgencies all
across the Far East of India the
northeast of India you have I can share
images if I Google them of of in of
separatist
leaders at the Great Wall of China at
the so-called Great Wall of China the
Chinese have done this for a long time
but right now what's happening right now
I don't think I I may be wrong but the
sense I get is that the Chinese may not
really be involved in this particular
thing although they'll be happy about it
and they may want to explore Avenues of
how to ex how to use this against India
but this most likely doesn't have too
much of a Chinese hand in it somebody
else and somebody more
powerful is probably behind this and
that's all I will say about this as of
now
okay um let us uh see some other
questions I mean ah Arian dor asks are
we close to the third world war okay so
let's examine the flash points in the
world right what are the the where is
the world messed up let's let's once
again go to the map because that's what
we do on this channel so here's the map
of the world the globe so where are the
geopolitical flash points right now well
we know that there's a conflict brewing
and ongoing simmering in the Middle East
the Israel versus Hamas andah conflict
right we have that now that's kind of
simmering right now it's not a very hot
conflict it's kind of going the slow War
route once again Israelis have some
presence in Gaza and all that and
they've captured certain you know places
and they seem to be intent on eventually
wiping out
Hamas uh so that's something that's
going on there is a some involvement of
hisbah in Lebanon as well in this so
there is a conflict here in the Middle
East and the Americans have deployed
two aircraft carrier strike groups in
this region one in the Mediterranean Sea
the other one in the sea of sashtra
which is erroneously called the Arabian
Sea okay but uh tan is out of range for
some reason so they have deployed
essentially the largest naval task force
since the second world war as a warning
to everyone not to go not to cross
certain lines so the Middle East is kind
of stabilized right now the other big
flash point is Ukraine once again we are
witnessing a very slow War there right
Putin Mr Putin we know what his
objective is his objective is to den
naify and de whatever eyes Ukraine de
deify Ukraine and obviously to effect a
regime change in Kiev to get rid of the
puppet zalinski and install his own
puppet there okay and maybe capture some
territory so he is eminently capable of
doing that but he's choosing not to okay
When The War Began in February 22
right the Russian forces were on the
outskirts of KV but they pulled back and
that's a whole story which I will not go
into right now but even Mr Putin is
going the slow is is taking the slow War
route because he's simply waiting for
the funding to dry up for Ukraine and
then he can just walk in and he's
prepared to wait as long as it takes
he's not in a hurry okay so it may take
another three years another five years
who knows so will go on so it's a it's
kind of Frozen conflict right now and
we'll see how the Israel thing also goes
that's another potential Frozen conflict
well the Middle East is a frozen
conflict it's always in crisis and it's
all because of external factors as we
know as my regular viewers would know
there's another flasho in the Taiwan
region there's another flasho as we know
in the India Tibet border the
undemarcated India Tibet border which
ranges all the way from Kashmir and
ladak all the way to arunachal Pradesh
right that's another long major flash
point um so yeah that's kind of it what
else do we have we have tensions in
Africa the Cold War has moved to Africa
there have been coups in the Sahel
region in the coup belt of Africa uh
which we have discussed so yeah so
that's the situation right now I don't
think we are really close to a global
global conf floration of World War I but
we aren't very far from it also it will
only take a couple of major mistakes or
just one major mistake from somebody to
set off something very big so yeah
that's the deal so I I I'm personally
not of the opinion that we are very
close to the Third World War when the
Ukraine conflict
started it it looked like something
could happen but the Americans have
wisely not put boots on the ground they
using proxies Ukraine is a proxy and
other proxies also are there in the line
so pipeline so yeah as long as there a
proxy conflict it's not going to cross
certain lines the Israel issue also is
kind of simmering down there was talk
earlier of Israel potentially having to
resort to the last use of I mean the
Samson option the use of nuclear weapons
that would cause I mean retaliation from
other nuclear Powers potentially Iran
Iran may possibly have nukes possibly
okay so right now it's it's kind of
under control but the tension the the
conflict is always just below the
surface so I don't think we are very
close to World War I I hope it never
happens but there we are right
now
okay
um simant kriti says Israel and the US
have accused Iran of hampering the India
Middle East Corridor India middle east
Europe trade and transportation Corridor
whereas the sord loser in this is China
my thoughts okay once again let's go to
the map here's the map so the India
middle east Europe trade and
transportation Corridor was something
that was agreed upon it was it was
announced during the G20 Summit which
happened a couple of months ago in the
last two months in New Delhi I was there
so uh it was announced and it was
announced by the US so the US has has
had thrown its full weight behind it and
this was supposed to be a trade and
transportation Corridor that would link
India with the middle east region Oman
Saudi Arabia all that and this Corridor
would then go
into Israel Via Jordan bypass turkey and
go into Greece and this was going to be
it can still be a GameChanger when it
comes to uh trade and
transportation um and it could be a big
uh alternative of major and attractive
alternative to the Chinese brri belt and
Road initiative and as we know many
nations in Europe are now pulling out of
the BR the Bri hasn't really done much I
mean the CH the the Pakistan uh leg of
the BR the cpec China Pakistan economic
Corridor has not really fructified it
hasn't really happened it's not really
going anywhere and the one of the major
problems for the for the B is the
Ukraine conflict because now the the B
the buildt all the infrastructure was
supposed to pass through Ukraine it's an
enormous country in Europe and because
of the conflict is not happening so the
IMC is a potential great alternative to
the B and one that is attractive to lots
of European nations because China is not
involved so
uh I'm not sure if Iran is behind this I
mean who set off the Middle East
conflict which we are currently seeing I
mean we know that Hamas and hisbah have
very deep and very strong ties with
Iran uh so it is possible
but the sore loser in this is not China
if the imch doesn't happen it's actually
good for China right so this is an
evolving situation it's still evolving
as we speak it's going to keep on
changing uh if the Israel conflict can
simmer down then the imch can still go
ahead the Saudis actually wanted this to
happen within a month and a half of the
announcement they wanted the
construction of the infrastructure to
start immediately
so Saudi Arabia is very bullish on this
uh Greece is bullish on this Italy
during the during the G20 Summit Italy
announced and informed the Chinese that
they are pulling out of of the BR it
would have been great for Italy as well
so I think it can still go ahead but as
long as the imic doesn't happen it's
actually good for China so that's the
situation and it's going to keep
evolving
okay um
okay let's take a question from Tes why
did Mr Gandhi not become the prime
minister of Independent India how did he
become famous overnight after returning
from Africa from South Africa uh so
let's take the second question first how
did Mr Gandhi become famous overnight
after returning from South
Africa so listen when somebody becomes a
superstar overnight you you have to
understand it doesn't happen without a
great amount
of of of groundwork and a great amount
of of media and other activities of you
know it's it doesn't happen overnight it
it's it's so hard for someone to become
famous there are so many people who
desire Fame who crave Fame and they
never become famous and it upsets them
so much it hurts them it's so painful
they no matter how much they try they
don't get famous and then there are some
people who become famous overnight
magically you cannot become famous
unless there are two ways of becoming
famous you either have to put in a lot
of work for a long period of time a
decade two decades yeah or you can
accelerate this process using a certain
fuel which is
money now to become globally famous
let's say let's say how to become famous
overnight in an enormous subcontinent
sized Nation like undivided
India it would either take somebody a
few Decades of hard work or an enormous
amount of money or the cooperation of
the media and the government at that
time the government was that of the
British occupiers of India the British
government of India the British
occupation government of
India yeah so how did he become o
overnight famous overnight that's
something you know we need to look into
history and ask examine these questions
aresh and that's why I have been saying
the things the the things have been
saying that most likely the British
wanted Mr Gandhi to take over the
leaders of the congress party the
congress party itself was a creation of
the British it was founded by Alan Hume
who was a British official in occupied
India the congress party was a British
creation and they wanted most likely Mr
Gandhi to become the overall leader of
the congress party because they had
observed his actions in South Africa his
activities in South Africa for a quarter
Century I mean nearly 25 years right and
they were confident that he would be a
valuable asset for
them uh so most likely that's the thing
so once he came to India he was all the
newspapers all the media started
showering Praise on him such a great
freedom fighter from Africa South Africa
who did such great work and when it's
all over the newspapers and they
constantly say the same things day in
and day out the person becomes famous it
doesn't take a lot and all the
newspapers were controlled by obviously
by the British government by the
occupation government of India the
British government so they would do what
they were
told so and and the Congress leadership
the congress party leadership well they
also you know could have been controlled
see the British created the congress
party for a certain purpose they wanted
to Stage manage and control the freedom
struggle in India they knew that there
are they they learned the lessons of
1857 that this can very quickly go out
of control and when the Indians take up
arms if the Indians decide to take up
arms and do or die it'll take 24 to 48
hours to eliminate all foreign occupiers
in India that's how long that's as long
as it will take 24 to 48 hours so they
had to give the Indians the impression
that there was this political movement
mement Freedom Movement that was on
their side that was fighting the British
but they wanted to be it to be
completely nonviolent and
Toothless so I think that explains
things I mean you can read between the
lines a little bit I I haven't let left
a lot to your imagination but that and
why did Mr Gandhi not become PM of
Independent India because
well it's always better to be behind the
scenes and have more power you know
when when in 1946 the vote happened in
the congress party all the regional
Congress committees they came together
and vot they decided to vote for the
person who would become the first prime
minister of uh the Dominion of India
Dominion
status so then we know that everyone
except one or two voted for Sardar Patel
there were a couple of abstentions and
then Mr Gandhi decided that he will go
on a fast till death unless everybody
agrees that Mr nehu becomes the prime
minister so he arm Twisted everybody and
Mr Neu was made the prime minister of
India despite not getting a single vote
do you know that in 1947 when Mr Gandhi
pulled off this
coup he was not even a member of the
congress
party he was not a member of the
congress party he had resigned earlier
like several years earlier so a person
who is not even a member of this
political party had so much power over
it that he
forced it to go against its own
Democratic vote so he was the person
behind the scenes who held the actual
levels of power now I'll not go into
details about how power Works power is a
very invisible thing it's very hard to
comprehend okay but he was the real
power in the congress party despite not
being a member of the congress party he
always wanted to be behind the scenes
the real power who doesn't have any
responsibility that the prime minister
actually would have so imagine that you
have a situation where one person is the
official leader of a Nation official
leadership comes with a lot of
restrictions and rules and regulations
and dos and
don'ts and then there is a person who
holds the actual power but has no
official position then that person is
free to do anything so only those who
understand power will get
why sometimes it's better to be behind
the scenes like when
when the Great vishnugupta chanakya was
essentially the power in India true
power in India even though Chandra Gupta
Maia was the official emperor of India
that sort of thing so Mr Gandhi did not
want to become Prime Minister he wanted
to be the power behind the Prime
Minister the real power in India so
that's kind of how it was and probably
the British also wanted Mr nehu to be
the Prime Minister he was a
very um he was a great anglophile he was
somebody they trusted and and so on so
forth so so yeah that is the deal that
is the deal all right all
right
okay uh Brian Oblivion the whole Indian
Revolution was kind of a farce to begin
with a passive Revolution that doesn't
work without power behind you well
that's yeah Indians don't get this
because Indians have been indoctrinated
by the education system in worshiping
individuals yeah see
it the same thing even goes for sports
and all that Indians don't really
understand Sports in great detail but
they worship individuals and if you say
something about that individual if you
point out certain things factually they
will ignore the facts and they'll attack
you so uh that's what happens so yeah
the Indian Revolution was a farce after
1857 it was all stag managed by the
British a passive nonviolent Revolution
I mean come on what kind of a joke is
that but yeah I mean Indians don't get
it I mean that's what the education
system has done to Indians first of all
it has created these uh personality
Cults around people like around people
like Mr Gandhi Mr Neu and so on that
these are Godlike figures you have to
worship them don't question anything
about them don't raise questions and
secondly it's taken the education system
has taken away the ability of Indians to
think critically Indians simply don't
know how to
think the first thing what to do you do
to take away someone's ability to think
critically is to
dissuade them from asking questions
that's what that's what the Indian
education system does you don't ask
questions you're not allowed to ask
questions so then you simply take things
at face value you stop asking
questions and that's what happens you
know so Indians simply don't ask
questions I mean thankfully there are
people who are thinking differently now
but it's still a long way to go so yeah
I
agree
um all
right uh what else what else what else
there are lots and lots of questions but
let
me um Dre vade says is this shiin Pink's
weakest phase is China's leader what are
the chances of him stepping down from
the post of the general secretary or
overall leader of the CCP I think Mr
shei has really Consolidated his power
and his position in the Chinese
Communist party uh apparatus he has
removed anybody who could be a Potential
Threat or potential Challenger to
him uh he has purged the Army there are
people who disappear for the smallest of
reasons yeah I mean the where is the
defense minister of China what happened
to him where did he go what happened to
the foreign minister apparently he had
an affair with some media lady come
on as long as he do he does his job
properly who cares but you know these
are all excuses all pretexts to get rid
of various individuals you find some
excuse and you get rid of them so what
Mr Xi Jinping has done is that he has
Consolidated Consolidated power
tremendously So within the Chinese
Communist Party um he has eliminated
much of the opposition any potential
opposition even the hint of a dream of
any anyone opposing him has been removed
but obviously there are smart people in
the CCP the CCP is a very tough
environment really really tough
environment dog dog dog e dog that sort
of thing during his rise Mr Shin Bing
made lots and lots of enemies I'm sure
he has kept lists and he has uh
marginalized or or purged most of them
but yeah there will still be enemies
there'll still be people who will look
for the slightest chance of weakness or
the slightest error and then something
would happen so I don't think it's his
weakest phase as China's leader but who
knows what's brewing within the Chinese
Communist Party who knows uh there's
when it comes to a dictatorship like
China there's always the possibility
that anytime something could happen and
the leader could be replaced I mean okay
let me give you a very bad
example uh there's an organization in
the US a company called open AI what
happened yesterday Sam wman was was
suddenly removed he was fired he was
sacked from his position as the CEO is's
out so these things can happen over
night I'm I I know it's a bad example
because this is not a dictatorship one
is a company in the US and one is the
Chinese dictatorship but but yeah my
point is things can happen suddenly so I
don't think it's the weakest phase of Xi
Jinping it may be his strongest phase
actually but all it takes is one error
one mistake or one setback you make a
you make a stupid error everything comes
crashing down if Mr shijin Bing let's
say hypothetically orders an invasion of
Taiwan or orders or starts a war with
India and things don't go well then he
he looks weak and in a nation like China
dictatorship like China the greatest sin
is failure right in India your leaders
can fail hundreds of times nobody says
anything they're they're Gods I'm
talking about people like Gandhi and Neu
and whoever else they can fail and maybe
some other leaders in certain political
parties in India today I'm not taking
names so all right but yeah certain
leaders can fail 78 times and nobody
says anything they still worship them in
a place like China One failure and
you're out so that's always a sword that
hangs over the Chinese leaders but but
that's what makes that nation and that
party so ruthless and so efficient but
yeah it's dangerous and it's
scary uh if you're in there
okay
um let's see what else okay let us see
this question ien read it let me see
Arian viam Singh if the Arian Invasion
migration tourism Etc theory is is wrong
and it was the harappans who migrated
eastwards and why do we see a decline in
the indust culture such as the
infrastructure town planning draining
system
Etc H good question we need to ask these
questions and have them answered so who
are these Harens I mean we are Harens we
are the descendants of The Harens first
of all okay um okay so okay let's go
back to let's say 5,000 6,000 years
before today 5 6,000 years before today
you had the great cities okay let's go
to the map and check it check out where
this
happened so you had this great phase of
India civilization in the west north and
the west of India okay the uh
northernmost uh Indus Valley or harapan
or whatever site sarasti Hindu site U
archaeological site that we have
discovered is in Northern Afghanistan
almost on the Tajikistan border okay and
it the southernmost such archaological
sites are found in in Northern
Maharashtra this went all the way into
madhya Pradesh madha Pradesh and all the
way west almost into Iran enormous
region okay where you had this flowering
pay of in Pay of Indian civilization
called the harapan phase sarasti Hindu
phase sapu phase whatever you want to
call it indust Valley
phase right so the greatest the the uh
the mature haran phase socalled so see
the
oldest archaeological site of the
harapan phase is found in birana in
harana that is about 9 and a half
thousand years old almost 10,000 years
old okay and the mature phase was around
5 6,000 years before today that's when
you had the great Metropolitan era
everything was it was a great
urbanization of this entire region and
standardization standardization of
weights and measures and urbanization
means great cities with multi-or
buildings and Incredibly Advanced uh
hydroengineering Drainage Systems flush
toilets um you know uh technology and
all that and even The Villages were like
that but not that big so tremendous
urbanization there was the phase okay uh
so the the British and the Indian
historians also called this the Indus
Valley Civilization haran civilization
and so on so forth and was centered
around the rivers in Western and
Northern India Northern Western India
the saasu region the Seven Rivers out of
which six still exist one has
disappeared but we can still find its
dry riverbed which was the greatest
river of India the largest river the
Saraswati way bigger than the synu okay
enormous river the mother of floods and
so on so what happened is
this we know that these great cities
were all abandoned eventually yeah they
are in Ruins today we still find the
ruins and over 95% of the ruins have not
even been excavated over 95% of the
archaeological sites that are known to
exist have not even been explored yet
and most of them are along the dry
riverbed of the salasa so why was all
this abandoned what happened it's
because of climate change my friends
climate
change about 8,000 years ago uh 6,000 BC
or so the Indian Monsoon was way heavier
than what it is today and around 6,000
BC the Indian Monsoon started declining
monotonically mean slow steady decline
over the centuries and Millennia and
eventually around 1500 BC or so much of
the sarasti had dried out and there was
a you know
much much reduced monsoon in the region
which could no longer sustain these
enormous cities and all the sement that
that bu been built up in this region so
what you saw was a slow steady gradual
de deurbanization and migration over a
period of almost, 1,500 years it did not
happen overnight that over right
everyone decided to leave the cities no
it happened slowly steadily gradually
lots of these the people who lived in
this region they migrated eastwards
northwards some of them even migrated
westwards
okay and it's interesting that around
5,000 years before
today we find the sudden influx of
Indian genetics in
Australia we also have the yamnaya
invasion of Europe and you also have the
sudden appearance of Indian cattle in
the Middle East region and even in Egypt
all of this happens around the same time
around starting around 5,000 years
before today and it goes on almost until
1,000 BC this this migratory pattern out
of India and also lots of migrations
within India okay so these people who
were who had to migrate away from this
region they settled in various parts of
the world most of them came in eastwards
but many of them went northwards many of
them went
westwards and some of them even even
ended up in
Australia so that's what happened
because of the decline in the
monsoon the rivers and this region could
no longer sustain such enormous cities
and settlements and people slowly moved
out of of this region over a period of
more than a thousand years it was a very
slow gradual process so that's why these
cities eventually got abandoned and you
saw a decline in all the infrastructure
town planning blah blah blah all that
that is what happened and that's what
the histor I mean if you read various
scientific papers dealing with
individual issues you will see the
pattern but our great historians don't
want to write about this they don't want
to speak about this they tell you a
different story so that is what happened
all
right okay let's have some more
questions okay this is a okay this is a
connotation but fog of war the fog of
war is the confusion that happens when
you are in the battlefield and there's
this battle going on and in the middle
of the battle with all the things that
are flying around and you're being fired
upon you're firing upon someone there
are explosions everywhere things get
confused and your plants may get thrown
out of out of the window the
communication lines may not all be open
so that is the confused situation that
you get when a battle starts and we when
you are in the middle of it that's
called the fog of
War okay
uh r farad says the Hindu Kingdom of
Champa which was in Vietnam built great
temples with beautiful architecture and
they still stand to this day in a ruined
State what's our government doing to
preserve
them I wish I knew I think there are
certain efforts being made to preserve
some temples U first of all let's take a
look at the map so that everyone
understands what we're talking about we
know where the Indian subcontinent is
which is our homeland I mean many of us
uh and then we uh let me uh deselect
this all
right
okay so the region we're talking about
is
Vietnam it's southeast Asia and you had
this great Kingdom called Champa which
was a one of the longest reigning
Empires or Kingdoms in this region
almost 1500 years and for a long time
they were uh vasal of the Chula Empire
okay and this was a Hindu Kingdom and
they built great temples and great
architecture in this region and you have
the temples in Mison let me see if I can
find this Mison
Vietnam
Mison so Mison there are temples here
there we go Shiva
temples uh Mison Mison I'm not sure
where the temples are because I've never
looked here but yeah what is
this there you have it there you have it
so you have these temples here these are
favorite Shiva temples in this
region
Cham as you can see much of their
culture is still deeply influenced by
Indian culture and it is their culture
it's their culture as much as ours and
it's a very uh unique
localized uh manifestation of our
culture so yeah this is the the group of
temples in Mison and I believe that the
Indian government has has has asked the
ASI to help the government of Vietnam to
uh preserve and to some extent restore
these temples and I'm sure something
like that is also being done when it
comes to uh the great temples in an
kurvat uh in Cambodia and maybe even the
great temples that still exist in
Indonesia so I think there is
some uh some activity in this guard
maybe some initiatives are being taken
but uh I'm not really clear as to what
the extent of this
is uh I think the government of India
should definitely take a great amount of
interest in preserving these
manifestations of Indian culture beyond
the subcontinent there's so much of it
in the subcontinent that we are no
longer in control of Vikram Shila is in
Bangladesh there's so much in
Afghanistan so much in Pakistan which is
being actively destroyed but when it
comes to these nations and cultures that
are friendly still friendly to us we
should certainly cooperate with them and
help them in
preserving uh these temples and other
great ancient
architecture uh so yeah it's something
we should do but I'm not sure to what
extent it is being done there is
something that's being done I'm I know
about it but how far what is the extent
of that I'm not sure
yeah
okay let us
see uh i s
okay another question one this is my
best thing did Chulas spread Sanskrit in
Southeast Asia or Sanskrit influence
Tamil because Tha and scripts are
descendants of Tamil palaa gr
script yeah so all these scripts that
you see in Southeast Asia whether it is
the Cambodian script the Burmese script
script uh the Tha and the K scripts and
all these are all
descended from various Indian scripts uh
and these Indian scripts whether it is
the palaa script granas script or
whatever script all of these scripts are
descended from
brahmi okay and brahi is way
older so that's how it is so we know
look uh when it comes to Southeast Asia
let's once again put southeast Asia on
the map let's display the map so during
the time of the Moria Empire during the
time of Ashok the great our great
emperor uh this region was called suomi
okay southeast Asia you go to Bangkok
today the airport the main airport there
is called snabi airport so this region
was called
snabi
and the first Contact
between Indian civilization and the
people of this region happened at least
3,000 years ago and the contact was
between the great people of orisha
orisha and this region so orisha had
this great great Maritime tradition and
they had this great Mercantile tradition
Merchants so they would send merchants
and Traders on ships to these regions
all the way to Cambodia Vietnam of
course Myanmar Thailand all of all of
that and you know various kingdoms were
established here which was which were
Indian and Hindu kingdoms Kingdom of f
for example the Champa Kingdom like we
spoke about and many more many more and
of course Indonesia all of these regions
were were
influenced so it was the people of
Kalinga that started this and then you a
thousand years before today you had the
Chola conquest of this region and lots
of these it it the Chola Conquest
extended all the way to the Philippines
so at various points in time you would
have had different various scripts that
were used in these regions and all of
these scripts would have come from India
so it's not just one script but there
were multiple scripts U there is this uh
inscription that was discovered in the
Philippines I forget the name of the
inscriptions it's on a gold plate it is
in Sanskrit I believe with some Filipino
local words something and I'm not sure
which script it is but it is definitely
not the gr script it's a different
script so you had different scripts that
were used at different points in time
over a period of almost 3,000 years at
least 2 and a half thousand years and
the the cholas they conquered this
region about a thousand years ago so
before the Chulas even came into the
picture you had other scripts that were
being
used
now so the use of Sanskrit in this
region started with the contact from
Kalinga about 3,000 years ago that's
when it started at least at least 3,000
years ago uh when it comes to the the
cholas there is absolutely no evidence
that they used anything except for
Sanskrit because this entire region
southeast Asia was already very familiar
with Sanskrit Sanskrit was the high
language The Prestige language across
the region and the cholas also were
extremely familiar with Sanskrit uh and
there are regions today for example in
Malaysia Etc Singapore where you have
lots of Tamil speaking people but those
Tamil speaking people migrated to these
regions quite recently during the
British occupation of these regions okay
so there was a time when India was
occupied by by the British Burma was
occupied by the British and much of this
region southeast Asia was also under
British occupation that's when the
British uh transported Indians as as
slaves to various parts of the world and
that's how many tamils got settled in
this region there are tamils who have
settled in Myanmar as well so all of
this is recent
migration okay that's how Tamil entered
these these areas
but historically it was
Sanskrit okay let's take another
question um feminist assassin says what
do you think of the coaching Mafia
destroying lives of students many
students are committing suicide you know
the coaching Mafia exists because of the
education system we need to reform the
education system so that this coaching
Mafia becomes completely
irrelevant that's what needs to happen
the coaching Mafia is is a well when you
have these high stakes exams which
students need to pass to get a job in
the government or whatever you know then
you will have these coaching classes and
coaching coaching Mafia we need to have
a better
system I'm not saying do away with all
the exams but we need a better system
and I I mean I'll not go into the
details right now I have at least three
episodes of ask abijit which deal
entirely with education I think it's
around somewhere around episode 30 so if
you're truly interested in in
understanding what is wrong with the
education system what needs to be done
and all that check out those episodes
it's somewhere around episode 30 or
something um check it
out okay
um oh what okay let's see this question
by Saga is it possible human history is
beyond 30 40,000 years or even more with
Mahabharata being a major event but the
West has changed the the timeline to
suit them well I can only answer on the
basis of evidence do we have evidence of
the Mahabharat well one of the evidences
of the Mahabharat that we have
discovered in the arch archaeological
record is the submerged city of dwarka
for decades our great historians laughed
at us that the Mahabharata is a
collection of myths it's all imagination
and myth mythology it has nothing to do
with the real world it's just a story
that's body came up with well in the
Mahabharat there is this event in which
Arjun visits dwarka and there is this
massive tectonic seismic event
earthquake huge earthquake and the
entire city of dwarka collapses and is
submerged Under the Sea okay and people
laughed at that because we have a city
of dwarka in Western India in sashtra is
there so what are you talking about the
city is there and then somebody Dr Sr ra
of the ASI de let me let me look and
Beyond the shore of the coast of dwarka
and see if I can find something and he
found an entire submerged City there so
clearly the city was submerged and then
a new city was rebuilt of the coast you
know on whatever
land remained and they have they have
done a little bit of research they've
done some carbon dating and one of the
pieces of wood that was dredged out of
the of this submerged City it was about
8 and half half thousand years old okay
it doesn't mean the city went under the
ocean 8 and a half thousand years ago it
means that piece of wood is that
old but uh so it tells you it gives you
a certain date limit or date range when
this would have happened so this seismic
event this this event of the city
sinking under the ocean happened less
than 8 and a half thousand years ago
roughly less than 8,000 years ago so
that gives us a certain timeline within
which the Mahabharat would have happened
okay I'm not saying it happened the
Mahabharat happened 8,000 years ago the
date is a issue of great controversy
because there are so many people who
have come up with different dates so
I'll not go into that so from the hard
evidence that we have it is clear the
Mahabharat happened sometime in the last
8,000 years we have to go by hard
evidence only we cannot let our
imagination run wild human history is at
least 100,000 years old at least it's
way older than 30 40,000 years uh
the oldest evidence of anatomically
modern humans homos
sapiens uh is from Northern Africa
Algeria the cave Cave of jabel hood it's
about how long is it how old is it about
four lakh years 400,000 years roughly I
may be wrong I've not looked at it for a
long time but something like that so
homo sapiens has been around for about
that long so and and our pre Homo
sapiens ancestors have been around for 2
three million years the human chimpanzee
Divergence happened about 4 million
years ago don't quote me on this but
something around somewhere around those
lines and the chimpanzees we know
genetically are our closest
relatives and so the Divergence happened
around four or so million years ago and
after that all the history that we have
is the history of our post Divergence
ancestors the ancient humans so human
history is very old but we have lost
most of it what we know is something
about the the the good evidence we have
is something that happened in the past
10 15,000 years the last ice age and and
after that um so the Mahabharat
definitely was a historical event it
happened somewhere in the last 8,000
years okay the M the ramayan happened
before that before the mahabat but when
exactly once again we're not sure and
there are people who have their favorite
dates and all that I will not go into
the controversy I'm sick and tired of
that fighting and bickering okay so I'm
I'm not going to go and Venture a date
but yeah that's a deal so I don't think
it's 30 40 50,000 years ago some people
make claims of God knows what I will not
take names and I will not go into that
at all but from the evidence that we
have it's clear clear that the
Mahabharat happened somewhere in the
last 8,000 years probably closer to
today than closer to 8,000 years
probably uh yeah so that's the deal
that's what I can tell
you Yash Singh borya says what's more
important for winning a war technology
or willingness to fight so first of all
you should be willing to engage in the
war if someone comes and attacks you or
someone is doing something naughty they
have to be dealt with so first of
all first of all first of all my dear
friends you need
leadership bunch of people there is no
decision by consensus there is no
decision through
democracy okay there is decisions like
these are only taken when you have good
leadership uh so first of all you need
leadership the right kind of leadership
the leadership that has the appetite for
risks and the appetite for taking hard
Choice decisions so that is the
willingness to fight it means you have
good leadership and leaders who can take
hard make hard decisions secondly you
can have have the bravest people and you
can have the largest armies that's
completely useless unless you have the
right
technology okay so in the 21st century
you don't even soon you may not even
need human soldiers you will have robots
that don't even that don't even look
human you'll have loitering drones and
all kinds of drones drone swarms and all
that you'll have missiles of various
kinds you will have UAV
uavs uh unmanned aial Vehicles once
again fighter planes will be entirely
remote controlled or or AI based and you
may not need human soldiers you have
those robotic dogs with machine guns on
them who can go and do things So
eventually it's going to be all about
technology also you will have cyber war
and all
that but historically historically
before all this technology came up you
still needed human soldiers and the
willingness to fight and good leadership
and well trained and disciplined armies
but what but but once again if you had
two forces let's say both have the same
number of soldiers both are disciplined
both are well trained in that case the
Tipping Factor was the
technology so that is how it goes you
need great leadership you need the
willingness to fight you need
well-trained disciplined Armed Forces
which means the train regularly as if
everyday is war okay no flab no fat
train every day and you need the right
technology technology is always the
deciding factor when you have evenly
matched sides
so there you
are Aran Vikram Singh says if the
harapan spoke Sanskrit then why did they
write in their own script and not in
Sanskrit and when did the DEA nagari
script become began being used so
understand the difference between a
language and a script
yeah a script is simply a container it's
a
vehicle okay let me show you some
something interesting since okay let us
go to Google and do a Google search Let
me let me show you
something uh where is Google
Google Google all right here we
are uh okay let me show you something
there is something called
[Music]
soomo soomo Script okay soyombo script
is okay statutory morning Wikipedia is
not always reliable but I'm going to
just use it for convenience here do not
trust everything that is on Wikipedia
especially when it comes to India it's
very biased against India but here we
are the soyombo script is a Mongolian
script okay it was developed by a
Mongolian monk in 1696 to write
Mongolian it can also be right to used
to write Tibetan and Sanskrit okay and
this is the soomo script it's actually
the swu script and one of the symbols in
the script the symbol is the
national symbol of Mongolia my point is
this that a script is simply a container
it's a vehicle it can be used to write
any language essentially you can use a d
nagari script to write English if you
want it won't be a great fit for it but
you can do it and today you can even
write Sanskrit and Hindi text in the
Latin script the English script right so
a script is it actually immaterial
Sanskrit has the Sanskrit language has
lots of scripts have been used to write
Sanskrit the karosi script the dagar
script the Sharda script the the gr
script the any script that is that
exists in India from north to south can
be used to write
Sanskrit so one of those scripts was
possibly the so-called harapan script so
what so
what the D nagari script came much later
I'm not sure when it emerged but
sometime in the last 1,000 years years
there have been so many scripts in India
and around India the Tibetan script for
example it's another script that can be
used to write Sanskrit so please
understand that so a specific script
being used to write Sanskrit or any
language doesn't mean that that that
language was prevalent or not prevalent
there a script is simply a vehicle it's
simply a container it doesn't matter you
can use dagar to write Tamil
also or Tibetan also and vice versa you
can use the Tamil script to write
Sanskrit of course you
can so understand a script is simply a
vehicle it's simply a container all
right and we don't know what the harapan
B I believe it's most likely srit but
and it it it all depends on the
decipherment of the so-called harapan
script and there has been some progress
on that and lots of claims but yeah once
it is properly deciphered and it is
established Beyond any doubt what
language it it encodes then we will know
what language was
spoken in those times in that region all
right I don't know why I get this
question so often am I of Russian
descent I am pure Indian bro I am pure
Indian there's no Russian descent in me
come on I don't know why people ask me
this uh okay let's
uh Miguel says why can't Indians
dominate MMA like dagestanis Brazilian
and Americans look in Brazil there is a
great tradition of these martial arts
gyms and all that and there's a lot of
awareness like in India everybody is
crazy about Cricket so everyone wants to
be cricketer in certain countries it's
all about MMA and Mi mixed martial arts
and fighting Combat Sports there's a
craze for that so everyone wants to go
into that and they have the facilities
for for giving young kids the right kind
of of training and the good coaching and
all that so who says Indians can't
dominate that it's not like Indians have
inferior genes or anything I mean so if
IND if if the same kind of
craze for Combat Sports occurs in India
then you will have the mushrooming of
gyms and training centers all across the
country right and they will go and look
for kids who are good at this and then
in a few years you'll have an explosion
of Indian martial artists so that's the
whole thing in India The Craze is about
cricket cricket cricket cricket so
everyone wants to hold a bat or mostly
it's everyone wants to bat that's the
thing so it's it's as simple as that
there is no awareness of MMA in India
very little today it's I think the
awareness is growing I have been
following MMA for a long time even
before anyone knew about it uh yeah so
that's that's a deal so in certain
Nations you have this craze for M that's
why there those Nations produce way more
Fighters than other countries it looks
like there's an over representation of
certain regions in MMA it's it's it's
because of this nothing
else
um let us see there are lots of
questions let me um take something
[Music]
interesting
uh one second let me me see let me see
let me see quickly I'll pick something
okay let's see this question from
theas theas says it's speculated that
methani Kings were of Indo Arian origin
how can that be when the local
population used Horan can Aristocrats
and locals be of different origin think
about the so-called mugal Empire in
India babber what language did he speak
doesn't even know he spoke the chagatai
language chagatai which is in extinct
turkic
language think about the uh what's it
called the so-called Delhi
sanet you know when you had Kings little
Chieftain like balban and ilut Mish and
that lady who was killed Raz Razia
Sultan or whatever what language did
they speak they spoke the chagatai
language right was it an Indian language
it was
not what did what language did
individuals like that guy orze speak
they spoke Persian is that an Indian
language it's closely related to Indian
languages but it's a Persian language
person right so you have so many
examples of the aristocracy the ruling
class speaking one language that is
completely unrelated to the language of
the people they rule over a thousand
years ago Anatolia turkey today's turkey
the Turks started infiltrating into this
region and they established kingdoms
there they spoke turkic languages the
locals spoke the local Anatolian
language once again the same thing when
the Europeans conquered North
America what language did the locals
speak the natives they spoke the local
Native American languages but the people
who are ruling their them spoke either
French or
English look at Australia today what
language the language do the natives
speak they speak local Australian
Aboriginal languages but the people who
are ruling over them speak a European
Germanic language English I can give you
a million
examples okay so that's how it happens
so it is not speculated that the miani
kings were of Indo Arian origin it is
known that the mitani aristocracy the
ruling class was Indo Arian how do we
know this because we have evidence of
this we have a peace treaty between the
mitani and the Hittites which was
found uh in the capital city of the
Hittites I forget the name
so they found this peace treaty on a
clay tablet and in this peace
treaty to seal the treaty a number of
gods are invoked Mitra varuna and so on
so forth all
Indian Vic gods were invoked in that
then there is a horse training manual
that was discovered in this
region uh the horse master who wrote
this manual for training war horses his
name was Kuli he calls himself Kuli the
mitani and it's a great manual it has
been translated into English and it is
it can still be used today to train
horses for war take a standard horse and
if you put him through this him or her
through the entire training period Then
you have a warhorse a well- trained
warhorse in this training manual which
is written in the local horian
language the author of this training
manual he there were certain
terminologies and terms technical terms
that he had to use to make the training
manual worthwhile but there were there
were no words for those terms in the
local huan language so he had to use his
own native language for that and his
native language was Sanskrit so it's the
first example we have of Sanskrit being
used uh it's the oldest of known example
of Sanskrit in in in literature in the
archology iCal record which strangely is
beyond India it's in present day Syria
yeah so this guy Kuli in his horse
training manual he used various Sanskrit
terms because those terms did not exist
in the huran language so clearly he his
native language his his indigenous
language was Sanskrit you know so that's
what so we have evidence that the
aristocracy of the of the metanis they
were of Indian origin Indo Arian origin
like they say and the locals used the
hodan language so that's what happened
all
right
uh uh we going to the very Basics now
ABCs are Arians originally Indians or
it's a statement Arians are originally
Indians there is no such thing as
Arians okay for us in the Indian
subcontinent ARA was a term that that
denoted a civilized person you call
somebody AR it's like calling somebody
sir today so a person who is well
behaved who is civilized who is you know
of that sort of standard in caliber was
called an ARA
person uh
and our cousins the Persians who aware
of Indian origin and long ago they went
out of India in the aftermath of the
battle of the 10 Kings which was
actually more than 10 Kings I'll not go
into that so then they the Persians
eventually they went west of India and
settled down where we know I don't have
to show the map for that so they started
using the term Arya as an ethnic term as
an ethnic self-d designator that we are
the ARA people okay but in the
subcontinent it it was not used as an
ethnic term it was used as a term that
denoted a civilized person a cultured
person a refined person so that's deal
so the person eventually started using
Arya as an ethnic self-d designator and
then the
Europeans the once they discovered India
and Sanskrit and all that then they
stole the term they stole the term and
then they created this fiction that the
AR the Arians are of European Nordic
origin and all that so yeah that's
that's that's the deal with
this
okay
um garit s says do you think the Indian
educational institutions can match or
possibly surpass Global standards
possibly attracting International
students here if yes how far off is it
you know when I was a little
kid you used to have students who came
to Indian universities students from
Eastern Asia from Southeast Asia student
students from Africa so those days there
was a certain standard that the Indian
education system had and before
2004 five whichever year that was before
then the
iits were often in the top 10 of uh
technological in institutions worldwide
and then something happened and the
education system was totally
ruined um so yes eventually Indian
education institutions if we reform the
education system thoroughly they can
once again be the best in the world I
mean historically who started
universities we did our ancestors did
you know Vish vial and all that the
great universities of nalanda Vikram
Shila URI Tara takshashila um so on so
forth so many it all started started in
India we are we had the best education
system in the world people from all over
the world used to come to India for
education shanang and so many examples
yeah and today what we are following is
the colonial education system it is
designed to ape the
west and it's going to take time to
reform that we going to have to reform
ourselves deeply starting with the
Indian constitution and the laws and the
governance system
and much much more so yeah say it's
going to take time but eventually we can
do it we can be the best in the world
once again yes indeed manasi says
chagatai yes that's that's indeed the
name name of the language which no
longer exists it was also the name of
one of chingis Khan's Sons
his which son was it second son the
oldest was Joi of course his parentage
was of was kind of Uncertain the second
was most likely chakat the third was
ogai and ogai became the next Emperor
anyhow yes Chata is the language
correct
um pray Kumar says is life just about
survival and entertainment well that is
the charvaka perspective charvak
perspective you know there are various
schools of thought in Indian philosophy
philosophical schools of thought one of
the schools is the charvaka thought
charvaka school of thought or the
materialistic school of thought which
says that the world that we see is the
only world that exists and the object
the aim of life is to enjoy the fruits
of the world and the resources available
to you and maximize your enjoyment in
pleasure and consumption and enjoyment
of the worldly pleasures and there's
nothing beyond that that's the charaka
worldview so from that perspective life
is about entertainment and pleasure and
survival so yeah that's a valid school
of thought in Indian philosophy even
though it's
the with all due respect the stupidest
and dumbest school of thought uh but
yeah so it's up to you it's your choice
what school of thought you want to
follow if you adhere to the charvaka
philosophy then life is about
entertainment enjoyment survival that's
it but if
you adhere to a different school of
thought then it's about something else
maybe something more than that so it's
you it's up to you who am I to tell you
what is right what's wrong you decide
what's best for you in life
right okay
all right here we go Arjun tiwari please
pick me well you're picked sir wish to
know about r1b ha groups prevalence in
India I did my ancestry DNA test and
found that my paternal ha group is a
subclade of r1b interesting okay so the
ha okay first of all to the to everyone
who's watching in case you're wondering
what's a haplo group a haplo group is a
bloodline a Hao group is a lineage you
can have two two kinds of H groups
patrilineal HP groups and matrilineal HP
groups patrilineal H groups are passed
on the the genes for that Hy group The
mutation is passed on from father to son
through the Y chromosome in your DNA and
the matenal ones are passed on through
the mitochondrial DNA from mother to
offspring men as well as women okay a
mother will pass on pass on her mat her
mitochondrial DNA to Sons as well as
daughters but it's only the daughters
who pass it pass it on to The Offspring
so that's how it goes so when a male has
a child is not going to pass on his
mitochondrial DNA to the child only the
patrilineal DNA the Y chromosomal DNA so
what's a HAPO group a hap group is a
group of individuals living today who
all share a specific genetic mutation
that happened in the past okay so for
example you have the
r1a R1 a Hao
group let's talk about a more specific H
group R1
A1A that's most likely an Indian origin
H group that is about between 18 to
25,000 years old and the number of
people who carry this genetic mutation
today all males they are more than a
billion today and they are found across
Ur Asia a huge concentration in Europe
and a huge concentration in the
subcontinent so that's what a Hao group
is it's an extended family of
individuals who all are descended from a
single ancestor who was the originator
of a specific genetic mutation now Arjun
is talking about r1b r1b is not that
prevalent in India which is interesting
okay let's go and check out the map of
r1b give me a second r1b
map let's go to images okay let me put
this on the screen shall I r1b map so
where is r1b prevalent worldwide as you
can
see it's not that prevalent in now in
India it's kind
of it's kind of uh greatly prevalent in
Western Europe some of it is prevalent
in U as you can see in this part of
Russia a large part large concentration
in Africa and very Less in India
strangely enough when you come to
r1a like I said it's different huge
concentration in India huge in Eastern
Europe so R1 a and r1b are both
descended from
R1 the parent Hao group so R1 is this is
the European map but it's all
across so if you include R1 a and r1b it
will be all across Eurasia so like I
like like we just saw
r1b is prevalent in Western Europe but
it doesn't mean that it would be it
would be completely absent in India so
Arjun seems to have a Hao group that
it's quite rare in India
r1b but that is not that surprising to
me because r1b is descended from R1
which is descended from R itself and I
believe it's going to emerge soon enough
that R and R1 themselves are Hao groups
that originated in India in the Indian
subcontinent or nearby so from that
perspective it's not that surprising but
yeah it's interesting that you have a
hlo group that's kind of rare in India
the r1b Hao group was the Hao group that
was prevalent in the majority of the yam
NAA Invaders who invaded Europe about
5,000 years ago four and a half thousand
years ago and that's and what the yam
Invaders did was that they completely
replaced the male genetics of Europe the
female genetics persisted after the
invasion but the original male genetics
were wiped out which means this was a
genocide a population replacement event
only killing of males yeah well that's
that's how history
is and the yam the yam Invaders well if
you see their genetics you can infer
their skin color hair color eye color
and you will know
that it'll tell you that their skin
color was not white it was light brown
light brown their hair color was brown
and their eye color was brown and their
hair color was dark so that's and and
they were genetically sturdy people
roughly six feet tall on average and
muscular yeah so so that's the genetics
that Arjun has
nice all
right let's
see hingh hatur says was nalanda
University destroyed by
Ki uh because some J professors on
Twitter are saying it was Brahman I know
that lady
yeah I'm aware of that uh the jnu lady
uh so some people on Twitter are saying
it it's those brahmins who destroyed it
is it just propaganda by gen professors
look at the original sources look at
what the Tibetans have written about
this various Tibetan see I don't have
all the data right now that I can pull
up and show you but do your own research
U there were various Tibetan Travelers
who came to India who wrote about what
happened one of them wrote who one of
them came to India in the aftermath of
the destruction of nalanda and when this
guy comes to to nalanda the University
was destroyed but there was still a
single Professor who was surviving and
he was still taking classes this guy
this gentleman his name was Rahul shirib
bhadra this professor he was in his
90s and he was still trying to continue
the classes and to teach
students okay and all these records all
these writers who came to India in the
aftermath of the destruction they all
wrote about the fact that it was this
guy bakar Ki who destroyed nalanda you
see brahans were not
warriors brahans were the preservers and
transmitters of knowledge and they were
also advisers of kings and all that in
certain
cases how can brahans destroy
University so this is pure
propaganda I I know at least one
individual on Twitter who goes on and on
about this I don't know what drives
these demented people I'm not taking
names so all right but yeah there you go
so it was destroyed by bakar Ki and the
sad thing is that nearby there's a
railway station called bakarpur that
honors that that terrorist that monster
that destroyed nalanda so let's let it
be very clear that nalanda was destroyed
by bakar Ki the turky Invader who had
destroyed much
more and uh when it comes to jnu well
what can I say what can I say
um okay let's see what
else shantu ja says India is weakest in
its Naval forces what's your thought
will it be able to counter China Navy
Force this is a good question it's a
controversial question but let's take it
up and there are lots of people who will
disagree with me well so be it can't
please
everyone so I would say that India has a
weak Navy but when it comes to comparing
the Indian army the Air
Force the Navy I would say the Navy is
kind
of kind of comparatively uh less well
equipped and funded that's what I would
say I think there's a whole lot more
that we need to do when it comes to our
Naval forces look at India's position
geographically India has a geographical
location that is a gift of the Gods
India dominates the Indian Ocean region
we can reach out anywhere in the in this
enormous part of the world because of
our great Naval location right so India
should be a great Maritime power
historically for thousands of years we
were a maritime civilization but today
we have what a Navy that is not that
strong the Chinese had a very weak Navy
in 1990 and then they started building
more
warships and it took them time to to
improve their
designs okay but today they have
possibly definitely the largest Navy in
the world they are churning out warships
destroyers frigates Cruisers whatever
submarines like they are churning them
out like sausages and quantity has a
quality of its own it does even if your
designs are not the best if you have
huge numbers it's going to overwhelm any
enemy so when it comes to the
numbers okay the Chinese Navy is way way
way larger than the Indian Navy you can
go and look up the numbers I'm not going
to do it here the problem that the
Chinese face is that they are bogged
down by the they are hemmed in by the
island chains there are three Island
chains one is Taiwan and all that second
is the Philippines and others the third
is Guam and way all that the Maria
Islands there are three Island chains
that encircle
China and there are these trouble spots
from the Chinese perspective one is a
huge threat from Japan Japan has a very
scary
the scariest submarines right U then you
have South Korea which is a US
possession so there's a huge us presence
over here which is danger for China then
you have Taiwan which again is under us
protection a US Ally so there's a
problem there so the bulk of the Chinese
Navy is deployed in the Yellow Sea the
East China Sea and the so-called South
China Sea which is actually the actually
the Champa sea the Chinese are also
claiming this entire South China
region as if this entire thing is is a
private Lake of China so they they have
to deploy the bulk of their Naval Assets
in this region and that's why even
though they have very the world's most
powerful navy this at least numerically
they still do not pose a great threat to
India as of today as of today they have
been deploying submarines in the in the
Indian Ocean region the Bay of Bengal
they have deployed subm Marines in the
andan nicobar vience you know on spying
missions they've deployed spy ships to
track Indian missile launches and Eaves
drop on Indian Communications in the
region they have this port in in
Pakistan called guad which was once
offered to India India rejected it
thanks to the great magnificent Mr neru
and they deploy some Marines there as
well they have a presence in this region
and they are slowly going to increase
the presence they also have this port in
jibuti which I can actually show you you
know they have a Chinese there's a
Chinese port in jibuti okay I'll not go
into the details right now because it'll
take time the point is they're going to
increase their presence slowly so what
does India need to do we need to
increase the numbers we need to build
more warships more submarines we need to
invest in distributed lethality and also
in numbers quantity has a quality of its
own we need to bolster the numbers of
various kinds of Warships
destroyers uh frig
submarines missile boats missile boats
can be a deadly potent weapon you know
and they're quite cheap a missile boat
is very cheap I mean you can build a
missile boat if you are Innovative for
about 1020 million which is peanuts you
know and put three missiles on each boat
brahos missiles scary scary scary from
the opposition's perspective and you can
put a 100 missile boats out there to see
or at least 30 or 40 and so so what
India needs to do is focus on the Navy
build large numbers of these assets of
course it's going to cost
money and if you we need more nuclear
submarines attack submarines U missile
launching submarines we need
conventional submarines as well see I
would say India needs at least 50
submarines what how many submarines do
we have that are operational today 12
13 guaranteed it's less than 20 for a
nation of India's size having 12 to 13
or 15 submarines it's a joke we need at
least 50 ideally 100 submarines of
course it's going to cost a lot of money
but if you want to be safe that's what
you have to do and there is this
Obsession here we go this is the
controversial part and lots of people
will disagree with me there is this
Obsession in in the Indian Navy for
building aircraft carriers I totally
disagree with that of course we have a
couple of aircraft carriers good but now
use the money to build more of these
assets distribute your lethality don't
concentrate it in one place so that's
what I would say there's a whole lot
that can be done and should be done and
I'm sure some of it is being done but we
need more we need more we always want to
keep improving we always want something
better and something
more
okay what do I think of Kur
ethnicity good ethnicity Indo Iranian or
Iranian whatever you want to call it and
they don't have their own nation and
that's why they are persecuted by the
Turks by the Iranians by whoever
else um and you had many great Kurds in
the past I mean they the Kurds I think
they were converted to Islam sometime
around the time the Persians were
converted to Islam after the Arabic
conquest of Persia which happened about
I don't know 1300 years ago
roughly um and the Kurds also got
converted and then they produced people
like salahudin ayubi and all that some
of the great uh Heroes of the Islamic
world so yeah that's what it is so the
Kurds are an indo-iranian or or Iranian
ethnicity an ethnic group that doesn't
have a nation of its own and that's why
they are deeply persecuted and
marginalized the Turks talk
about Mr erdogan the president of Turkey
he talks about the horrific persecution
of the people of Gaza by the Israelis
what's he doing to the Kurdish people by
the way what is he doing isn't he doing
the same persecution but no one talks
about it so that's that's the way the
world operates so yeah that's
what
okay Ana says China has not intervened
in any military conflict they have not
attacked any country in the last 50
years on the other hand we know how the
US has intervened worldwide then why
does China have such a bad Global image
okay
um when was the last time they attacked
a country 1979 was when they invaded
Vietnam and they suffered a disastrous
defeat
79 so that's 20 so that's less than 50
years my dear sir or lady whoever you
are yeah so it's not true that China has
not attacked any country in the past 50
years okay they also tried to fight
India in 1987 and they were
defeated okay so the what Clash suong
Chu Clash or whatever I don't remember
what it was called but there was a mini
war in 1987 the Chinese tried a 1962
kind of thing and they were beaten
back okay the Chinese let me tell
you they occupy Tibet Tibet has never
been Chinese they are conducting
cultural genocide in Tibet they have
banned the Tibetan language all schools
in in every school the kids have to
learn their do their education in the
Chinese language So eventually it will
wipe out of the Tibetan language and the
CH the Tibetan people are not allowed to
practice their culture there is a
similar occupation of the east turkistan
region which was never Chinese again
half of Mongolia is currently under
Chinese occupation what you see of
Mongolia is only half the nation you see
these places these these regions are all
part of what the Chinese called inner
Mongolia north of Beijing is where in
inner Mongolia starts okay you have
these mountains around that that protect
Beijing that have historically protected
Beijing if I show you the terrain you
see these mountains that have
historically protected Beijing North of
that is in inner Mongolia the GOI desert
so that is under Chinese occupation and
then you have manua which is not Chinese
again under Chinese occupation the
Chinese are claiming the South China Sea
which I mean what business do we do they
have being there it was historically the
Champa sea the Taiwan is a whole
different issue so the point is they
fight they are they and look at the
number of Border disputes they have they
have border disputes with all their
neighbors they're trying to bite away at
little Bhutan they have a huge
undemarcated border with India they
claim Afghan territory they claim tajik
territory they claim kgis territory they
have reopened a border dispute with
Russia in the
East okay they have a border dispute
with Japan I can just go on and on how
will a country like this have a good
Global image please explain to
me please explain to me how will a
nation that behaves in this manner have
a good Global
image they use Deb trap diplomacy to
trap little Nations like Sri Lanka
little nations in Africa they're
extracting wealth you know resources Out
of Africa which is okay which everyone
does but they prop up dictatorships they
trap nations in the these dead traps
then then take over the territory
they've taken over the Hanta port in Sri
Lanka how can such a nation have a good
Global image and of course of course the
Americans are no better they they
actually are worse you are right about
this you're right yeah but the Americans
control the global media they control
Hollywood Hollywood what look at watch
Hollywood movies about
American soldiers and American military
operations they always portr the
Americans as as a good guys right the
media is entire the English speaking
media the Western media is entirely
controlled by Americans and the Indian
media simply copies what they write or
say right so that's the deal so that's
why the Americans have a great
reputation and the Chinese have a bad
reputation I'm not saying the Chinese
bad reputation is
uneed it is well
deserved yeah the Chinese they deserve
their bad reputation so yeah there you
are
okay you
says what's your opinion please on
Indira Gandhi the former prime minister
who was assassinated was she a good
leader or bad leader of India I know
things are complex
look
um it's a good question she was
definitely a strong
leader
uh she is the person the the leader who
gave the goahead for uh the liberation
of Bangladesh in
1971 right so definitely she did many
great things of course she believed in
socialism and uh there's this book by
leanu okay his Memoir he has he there
are a number of books in which you have
lean you speaking about various things I
don't remember which book it is but I
have some of those in one of these books
he writes about in India and he says
that he visited India in the early 80s
or something okay and he met met Mrs
Gandhi and he told her that you know
Indians who live in Singapore they do
tremendously well they're extremely
motivated they're extremely
uh you know they they really do well
Indians wherever they are across the
world they are really hardworking
they're very intelligent they always
rise to the top of the society the top
stratum in the society they're very
entrepreneurial very Innovative and
Indians in Singapore are among the most
accomplished of Singaporean citizens so
and it's because of the way our
governance is we allow people we
encourage them to rise to the to the
fullest extent of their potential why
don't you unleash the latent hidden
power of India by reforming your economy
and the nation why did you do that
that's what he asked Mrs
Gandhi okay and she said this is the way
India is and this is how it will be
that's how this is how I want India to
be so she
was perfectly happy with socialism she
was happy with continuing the nean
Legacy okay so that's I would say one of
the weak points or or or if you are
talking about pros and cons that's one
of the cons when it came to Mrs Gandhi's
leadership in India but of course she
was very strong when it comes to
National Security she was the one who
gave the Indian army the go ahead to
liberate Bangladesh without her go-ahead
nothing would have happened right she
was a hardliner when it came came to
combating Pakistan and all that of
course during her time you had the
khalistan issue that that cropped up and
all so there are pros and cons like you
said things are complex but overall she
I would not say that she was a bad
leader yeah yeah so that's what I would
say
okay okay let's
uh and of course people will disagree
which is fine you can disagree socialism
was the need of the hour yeah okay I
disagree I completely disagree but yeah
there you
are the question is what does socialism
do what happened after
1991 the India India was on the verge of
bankruptcy and the Indian government was
forced to open up the economy and
become less socialistic and more
capitalistic what happened it totally
Unleashed uh the
entrepreneurial instincts of the Indians
and you know the Indian economy GDP rise
begins there and after 2014 all the
reforms that were done by Mr Modi and
his government you can see the fruits of
that coming in now and you can see that
India is the only economy that is not
going to have a recession it's the only
economy that is projected to ever
surpass the US yeah so what is that
socialism that did that
if India had opened up its economy and
and invited investment and all that and
copied what Japan did or other nations
did in from 1947 itself then India would
have been one of the top three economies
in 1991 itself so so so this I do not
agree with with with
respect
um cost of B say says will the US and
Russia start nuclear testing again
what's your take on it um I don't know I
think if one of them does it then the
other will also do
it I don't think they need to do nuclear
testing because they've done hundreds if
not thousands of nuclear tests already
their nuclear weapons are well
calibrated they know exactly how to get
things done so I don't think there's any
need for them to do nuclear testing if
they do if any of them does a nuclear
test it will be a political statement
not something that is actually needed or
necessary
and if one of them does it then the
other one will also most likely do it I
think Mr Putin has actually stated this
recently in the past few months sometime
that if the US does a nuclear test
conducts a nuclear test then Russia will
go ahead and do the
same so yeah so I don't know if they
have any need to do it but if it happens
it's going to be a political statement
more than something that happens out of
technological
necessity
uh moit R says my haplo group is r y7 in
one of one of your videos you spoke
about the out of India migration it's
the same haplo group as the malta boy
from Siberia also I'm a jart so now you
Haven me confused
look when we talk about out of India
migration it's one big wave or multiple
big waves but a migration is not never a
linear process you have multiple waves
of migrations and I never said said that
it's not possible that there was some
migration into India we know that even
during the look this not sure if the map
is needed right now we know that even
during the sarasti Sindu era the harapan
era there are there's the possibility
that many of the people whose bones are
found in various symmetries from that
time from 5,000 years ago many of them
could have represented first generation
immigrants to India when you have
a region a civilization that accounts
for let's say a half of the world's GDP
which is incredibly prosperous
technologically advanced great standards
of living everybody wants to migrate
there that's what everyone does wishes
today everyone wants to migrate to the
US right because that's the place where
you have the highest standards of living
and all that so in the ancient days it
was this region the Saras Hindu region
so everyone wanted to migrate to this
region and people would have migrated
from neighboring regions
yeah so you will have the exchange of
genetics that happens like
this so it's and see the the ha group
you're referring to R y7 it's a
descendant of r r is most likely an
Indian origin hrou see when it comes to
the matal hres that are prevalent across
the
world 95% of non-african females who are
alive today are descended from the
mineal hpo groups M and N M and N these
two matrinal haplo groups originated in
the Indian subcontinent between 60 and
70,000 years before today that's how old
they are and you will have descendants
of that all across the world so yes you
will have relatives of the of of so
there will be ladies in India most of
them who will be related to ladies
across the world who are not of African
origin so that's how it is it's it's
really complex so when it comes to the r
Hao groups and descendants like R1 R2 r
y whatever these are all descended from
an ancient hpo group R which most likely
originated in the subcontinent so if you
have this boy in Siberia this mummy who
was found who have this H group it means
that further back in time his ancestors
also would have originated probably in
the Indian subcontinent so that's how I
it's it's very confusing genetics is
very confusing all these ha groups and
all this terminology is like that the
thing is if you examine it's it's about
the lens that you use to examine history
length as in the time period if you look
at history from the perspective of the
last 200 years you will get a certain
picture of History if you examine
history from the perspective of the last
thousand years which is which is a
different lens you will get a different
image if you look at it from the length
of the past 5,000 years you will get a
different different picture if you if
you examine from from the perspective of
the last 60 70,000 Years you'll get a
whole different picture so it all
depends on which which time period
you're looking at so this Malta boy let
me see how old that mummy is ml T
boy Malta buth culture okay let me put
that on the screen and we'll take a look
at it
together okay so I'll once again just
take a look at Wikipedia just for
convenience so this is okay 24 23,000
years before present okay so it's it's
not that old the r Hao group is older
than
that
uh so there you go see the history we're
talking when we talk about genetics and
Hao groups we're talking about tens of
thousands of years tens of thousands of
years so this Hao Group which was found
in this
boy it is a descendant of older haplo
groups okay and R is way older let let's
let's see how old Wikipedia says R is
just let me quickly go
there uh Hao group
R let's see what it says ha group once
again why empty DNA I want to see r1a
Indian origin of Pat that's r1a H group
r1a is descendant of R1 which is
descended of
R so app Group R is about 27,000 years
old and it's probably place of origin is
probably the subcontinent or maybe
Northern Asia like they are saying most
likely the Indian subcontinent so the
Hao group R is an ancestor of this ha
group R y7 and ha group R is about
20,000 years old at least roughly let's
say so it's older than the ry7 so that
explains that explains the whole
situation now doesn't it so it all
depends on what time frame you're
looking at to examine a certain
issue all right
um okay POI says Salon G there was no
country concept anywhere in the whole
world okay this is a conversation that's
going on in the chat but let me speak
about this the nation state concept that
we are very familiar with we only think
about let's go to the map of the world
when we think about the world we think
about Nations we think about countries
right we think of India as a country we
think of our neighboring countries as
Pakistan and Nepal and then we have
countries all these lines on the map
denote various countries historically
there were no Nations there were
kingdoms Empires and
civilizations the nation say State
system is an artificial and recent
concept it dates back to the Treaty of
West fak two 300 years ago that's it
okay
so historically the concept of countries
and nation states did not exist it's an
artificial concept it was uh this
concept was created to to divide the
world up for
colonization uh by Europe it's a
European concept it's not a global
concept but today it's it's seen as a
universal concept because the whole
world is currently under this system
well you are now witnessing the slow
reemergence of civilization States and
Empires China is an Empire okay China is
an ancient civilization about 3,000
years old okay let's say three and a
half thousand years old if you want to
be nice to them but it's an Empire okay
Russia also is an Empire by the way the
actual homeland of the Slavic people the
Russians is is Western Russia all of
this that you have in Russia today it is
Siberia and Asia all the way to the Far
East of Russia okay so all that is
Imperial Conquest it's the consequence
of Imperial Conquest so Russia
is the it it carries the legacy of the
Russian Empire and China is is a modern
day Empire and the and the US is also an
Empire by the way but we call it a
superpower so the the term superpower is
euphemism for the for for Empire so the
country concept the nation state concept
is an artificial concept it's a very
recent concept it's never been there in
history and I think it'll soon disappear
in the next 50 to 100 to 200
years yeah that's what could
happen sorab says what what makes
Sanskrit the best natural language what
uniqueness did it have that others did
not uh our so-called great social
reformer Mr Ram Rohan mohanroy says it's
inferior yes Mr Ram mohanroy has written
about this he wrote a letter to the
British occupiers of India saying that
Sanskrit is an inferior language and it
needs to be smashed out of existence and
replaced with this great Superior
enlightened language called in called
English that's what Mr Ram mohanroy
wrote he was
uh yeah he was greatly opposed to
Sanskrit he believed it was inferior see
what what's unique about Sanskrit it's
the oldest
known Indo-European language okay there
are people who will say that no srit is
only so so and so years old and whatever
language in the Middle East region was
older that's that's nonsense okay uh yes
he was a Freemason that's right you got
it you got it right uh let's go back to
where is the question once again
it's G on okay so the point is sanskrit
is the oldest known Indo-European
language it's an extremely rich language
with a ridiculously Rich vocabulary
there are more than a 100 words for the
term see in English we have one word
called love in Sanskrit there are more
than 100 words that can be approximated
to mean
love okay SN PR and lots of words
so it's an incredibly Rich vocabulary
and each of these terms has slightly
different meanings that the English
language simply doesn't have the ability
to
express uh so yeah it's a it's an
incredibly Rich language and that tells
you how ancient it is the older a
language the more synonyms and richness
it will have and so on so that's the
thing about it and it's got a beautiful
grammar completely mathematically
algorithmic grammar and that was created
by the great Panini of course more than
2,000 years ago and before that you had
an older older versions of Sanskrit like
the like post VC Sanskrit Vic Sanskrit
and even previc Sanskrit which we are
not really uh very familiar
with so yeah that's how it was that's
what I can
say
now
um Arian suti says thoughts on viik
ramaswami very interesting guy he's he's
a very smart guy he's a very young guy
first of all Indian origin guy Hindu guy
who speaks about the fact that he's
Hindu he doesn't try to hide that and
he's a very smart guy I think he is
planning to run for president in 2028 or
Beyond right now he is his aim is to
become nationally relevant in the US
maybe globally relevant and maybe maybe
run as the vice presidential candidate
for Donald Trump I think that's his
objective and you will see see that he
makes it a point to never criticize
Donald Trump ever and he goes after
people in his own party and in the
Democrat Democratic party so very smart
guy he's playing the long game he's
extremely articulate he's a great
speaker he's always on the point he can
demolish any stupid question or
argument so yeah very interesting guy I
think
he's he's hoping to run as the vice
presidential candidate as as the partner
for Donald Trump in Donald Trump's
presidential bid in 24 so that's what I
think is doing very interesting
day okay
um Damini says there was no life on
Earth for a long time is it possible
that the Moon Mars and other planets on
which we are trying to search for life
these planets are facing similar
atmospheric conditions in the presentent
so the Moon is not a planet it's a moon
it's a satellite of the earth and the
most prevalent theory that we have of
the origin of the moon is that in the
early phase in the very early period of
the solar system when you had the
planets were still like molten Blobs of
rock or thereabouts so in the very early
phase of the solar system there was a
collision between Earth and another
planet which no longer exists so these
two planets collided it was a glancing
collision and lots of debris were thrown
into orbit around the Earth and within a
month or two this debris all this all
this debris they coales together and
formed what is now the moon okay so the
Moon is a satellite of the earth it's
tid tily locked in that's that's a
different story when it comes to Mars we
know that Mars once had so how old is
the solar system four something billion
years old and we know that life has
existed on Earth unicellular life at
least 2.7 million milon years before
today yeah we know that Mars once had
flowing water we know that Mars once had
oceans of H2O water okay so Mars was
very different in the past and what
happened to Mars is that it is a smaller
Planet so it it lost its magnetic field
because the inter interior of the planet
cooled down and in in in for Earth we
have this huge molten core which is
mostly metallic nickel iron and it it
has very different properties from metal
that we have on the surface it is under
extreme pressure and it is charged and
it is the moving charges that that cause
the that create the electromagnetic
field of the earth which Shields our
atmosphere from solar radiation from the
solar wind Mars lost its magnetic field
because of which the solar radiation was
able to impact the atmosphere and the
oceans of Mars and stripped all this
away over a long period of time so
that's why Mars lost its atmosphere and
its oceans we still have frozen water on
Mars lots of it Bel below the surface
and also in the polar regions right so
it's possible that there may have been
Life on Mars a billion or so years
before today or maybe even before that
it's possible and we may have found some
circumstantial evidence for that yeah so
so Mars was very different in the past
today it's it's a mostly dry planet with
a thin atmosphere spere uh so yeah it's
it's changed over time and the Earth
also will change over time the next few
billion years the earth will be very
different from where it is today and the
sun itself will be different so that is
how it goes you know solar system will
evolve the sun will eventually become a
red giant it will engulf the orbits of
Mercury Venus and the Earth only Mars
will be left out and eventually the sun
will Shed off its external layers when
the nuclear reactions fizzle out
and it'll create a big nebula around
itself and what will be left at the
center where the sun is is a white dwarf
okay and the Earth will be burned to a
cinder that's what will happen
eventually in about five billion years
from today so that's how a stellar
system typically evolves over time okay
any updates about World Cup finals and
khalistani threat so I have not heard of
any khalistani threat to the World Cup
final but yeah the final match is
tomorrow so yes go India we're going to
win we're going to win and we're going
to take revenge on the Australians for
2003 I watched that final match 2003
yeah and it was not a good experience so
this is a very different team India this
time so I I hope we win tomorrow I
follow sport I am a huge sport fan I not
just Cricket but I watch hockey I watch
martial arts football all of that c I
like K as well great Sports so I hope
India wins tomorrow
yes okay
um uh what else do we
have okay Manoj Kumar says why can't we
state facts as our opinion on Mr Gandhi
in cbsc board exams why would we have to
only praise him just to get marks facts
are facts and they aren't even if they
aren't written in hisory in Inc
textbooks facts are facts but your
examiner is going to fail you if you
write what is not in the textbooks that
is the problem with the Indian education
system you may know you may have
knowledge that is superior to what's
written in the textbooks but you have to
pretend to be stupid and not know
anything and only write in the exams
what's in the textbook I
have I have faced such idiotic
teachers I mean their slavish devotion
to textbooks is so incredibly
frustrating I remember which standard
was I in 7th or something I don't know
which standard it was we had the subject
called science okay science in in
in there was a science textbook and
there was some kind of scientific
circuit diagram or apparatus or
something which was part of which was in
one of the lessons and I that that came
up in the question so I drew the diagram
from my memory and my understanding and
I drew it in a different way from what
was in the textbook and my teacher she
gave me zero marks she said it's not
exactly as per what is in the textbook
it was completely correct from a physics
perspective but it was not exact an
exact copy of of what was in the
textbook and she gave me zero marks for
that she was
stupid okay this teacher I mean there
are so many examples and incidents like
everybody all all of us would have so we
to understand that our teachers and our
education system
are still fully colonized okay and if
you write truths then you're going to be
failed in the exams so that is where we
are today so if you want to so you can
either fight the system and be beaten by
it or you can use the system to get
ahead in life and then speak the truth
on a bigger platform then in the exam
what's the point of trying to speak the
truth in the exam you want get marks and
you won't get what what the what your
objective is which is your degree or
whatever so I think we have to be
realistic and practical in life we know
what the truth is but to treat the
education system and exam and exams as a
tool that will allow you to get ahe in
life yeah so it's the way it is ideally
you should be able to state facts but
that's the way our system is it's still
very
backward what's the point what's the
point so long ago it doesn't matter
anymore there are a million teachers
like that you all have to deal with them
yeah
uh I
mean okay last time I didn't answer you
see during a live stream I get maybe two
3,000 questions at least I can answer 20
or 30 of them so I apologize to those of
you whose questions I'm not able to
answer I really appreciate that all of
you are ask so many questions but this
is what happens do you believe the
concept of satyug in a solar system was
closer to a superstar super Sun all
that look the Yuga system is very
interesting
okay
um was the solar system close to a
superstar there have been stars that
have come close to the solar system okay
in the past I mean about 880,000 years
ago there was a star called Barnard star
which is right now very dim and faint
but it was once it once passed very
close to the Sun like just a handful of
light years away it may be even the it
may be even interacted very closely with
the solar system and it may have
influenced certain events in the solar
system so these things happen it was not
a superstar it's just a regular star uh
so it's happened it it would have
definitely happened in the past that our
solar system came in came in close
proximity with other stars and it would
definitely have effect the
evolution of our solar
system so that is what I can say about
this entire matter but that's an event
the the nearest event was about 880,000
years ago so that is way way way before
any of these historical events that we
can think of like the ramayan maharat
ETC happened so so I'm not sure if there
is any
correlation maah Roma m F Rahman Sor
says where did Europeans come from
before the Indians invaded them was
Iranian Neolithic Farmers originally
from Iran or where they also out of out
of India migrants that is still an open
question okay there is a genetic
research that's been that is currently
being done in within India outside of
India there is the what Golden Crescent
Theory or something Fertile
Crescent or something some the latest
one of the latest papers which says that
the uh origin of the Indo European
languages was further east maybe in
present day Iran so earlier it was
Eastern Europe then it became Central
Asia now they have moved to Persia give
it a decade it'll move into India that's
the thing okay so
uh it's it's a very complex topic where
did Europeans come from before Indians
invaded them look
about 10 15,000 years ago the people who
lived in Europe had dark skin and blue
eyes weird okay the the genetic mutation
for fair skin and blue eyes sorry the
genetic mutation for fair skin and red
hair or blonde hair it only originated
about 10 or 12,000 years before today
and that two originated most likely in
either Persia or India
okay so the fair skin that we see in
Europeans today it came from further
east but it suddenly somehow became more
prevalent there because of whatever
reasons
uh so yeah the ancestors of today's
Europeans obviously uh are a mixture of
the females who lived in Europe long ago
and the yam Invaders who came from
further east let's say okay so yeah it's
it's it's all of this is still a subject
of research great amount of research
there is still from a genetic
perspective a great lack of clarity and
this is something that's going to keep
on uh research is going to continue it's
going to take maybe 10 20 30 50 years
perhaps to have way more clarity on this
matter but it's clear that a large
amount of the genetics of Europe came
from further east most likely from the
Indian subcontinent the genetic mutation
for fair skin also emerged emerged about
10 or 12,000 years ago most likely in
the subcontinent but most of it most of
that those genetic components went for
the West into Europe the Iranian
Neolithic farmers are are now supposed
to be The Originators of the Indo
European languages well that is still a
work in progress so it's going to take
time to get more clarity on that um
where the out of India migrants time
will tell still
unclear okay we have way crossed two
hours almost two hours 10 minutes I'll
take one last
question
um okay what shall I take what shall I
take what shall I
take
um wasik says were The KES hites Turks
or ofans they were Turks the hites the
Sha hunas they came they invaded there
were Nomads who most likely originated
further east from India and they tried
to invade India about 1600 or 1700 years
before today during the end phase or the
second pH latter phase of the Gupta
Empire and at the same time they were
invading Rome successfully the Roman
Empire when it comes to India they kind
of failed but of course after the Gupta
Empire declined the Hep hites were able
to the shet hunas were able to conquer
Northwestern India which is presently
Afghanistan and gandhar and all that and
they became Indians they became Hindus
and some became Buddhists and then they
defended India from the Turks the Hindu
shahis yeah so the khis were and
Afghans well the Afghans were also
Indians gandhar right so the khis were
Turks they were neither hites nor ofan
they were Turks all right that is the
last question for today I apologize
those of you who have asked so many
questions and I was not able to answer
them apologies but thank you for all the
questions and we will keep on doing this
and I'll I'll hopefully answer
everyone's questions eventually so thank
you for watch thank you so much for
watching and I will see you in the next
session take care and like I always say
keep raising your standards and keep
working hard into reaching your true
potential thank you so much and I will
see you next time have a good day good
night wherever you are I'll see you L
later thank you